Guide to the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection, 2012-2020 RL.11067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2016
  - Creative Theses, 2016
    - Cunningham, Alex, 2016
      Western Disturbances, and Ice Brought down from the High Mountains. This collection includes a digital file of the video documentation of the performance Multimedia documentary Western Disturbances, which premiered at the Full Frame Theater in Durham, NC on April 16, 2016, as well as the original source video file for the performance. It also includes digital transferred video files of the four 16mm films that premiered as part of a collection called Ice Brought down from the High Mountains on April 17, 2016. The titles of these films are: twentyfive, Raining Ragas nos. 16, Borderlove, and Zeniths and Nadirs: the oscillations of beginning and so always.
      Cunningham's abstract: "The project Western Disturbances began as a fairly convention documentary project focused on the Indian Monsoon. However, while spending the 2015 summer in India attempting to document the rains that never came, the project shifted focus. It became a project about the specifics of the 2015 monsoon, the personal struggles in the making of the film, and the general ideas of failure, expectation, anxiety, and patterns. The end result of the project is a live documentary performance film. The film is narrated by the filmmaker live in the theater, and includes different media (including VHS played on a VCR/TV and 16mm footage projected) as well as objects and props such as newspapers, books, and lamps that give the film the feeling of a stage production. The expanded and chaotic physical nature of the performance creates an experience essential to the viewing of the work.
      Ice Brought down from the High Mountains is a collection of four short 16mm films shot, edited, and projected on film. The four films chart the formal, thematic, and stylistic evolution of the artist over two years. Experiments with structure in filmmaking run parallel to the ideas of uncertainty and instability explored in the works. twentyfive is an camera film of 100 feet of film with superimposed text. Raining Ragas nos. 16 is a silent, in-camera rhythmic film which was made to help induce the beginning of the monsoon rains. Borderlove is a black and white handprocessed dissonant love and travel metaphor film narrated by an alien colonialist explorer. And Zeniths and Nadirs: the oscillations of beginning, and so always is an attempted documentary of the birth story of earth and of the human psychology, including footage of volcanoes, frozen waterfalls, and the night sky."
      - Western disturbances, 2016; Two Apple QuickTime video files; approximately 52.2 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0008)
      - Ice brought down from the high mountains, 2016; Four Apple QuickTime video files; approximately 18.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0008)
    - Galanis, Tamika, 2015-2016
      Hacking the Narrative: Telling Counter-Tropic Stories. This collection includes 25 artist proof prints representing photographs and 4x 3D printed Human Coral Hybrids, which were shown in a collaborative MFA thesis exhibition with Jon-Sesrie Goff at the Jameson Gallery, Duke University from April 11-24, 2016. Also included, is the film 'When the Lionfish Came' which screened at the Full Frame Theater in downtown Durham on March 27, 2016 as part of Tamika Galanis's MFA thesis exhibition in Spring 2016. Galanis's abstract: "Emphasizing the importance of Afro-Bahamian cultural identity for cultural preservation, this work documents the aspects of Bahamian life, which are not curated for tourist consumption. These art works counter the widely held paradisiacal view of the Caribbean, the origins of which arose post-emancipation through a controlled, systematic visual framing and commodification of the tropics."
      - The constituency (photographs), 2015; 17 prints 2 folders (Box 25)
        This body of photographs represents the beginning of a lifetime of visual practice to intervene in the existing archive and accurately represent the Bahamas and Bahamian cultural identity. These images are representative of the Grants Town and Montagu constituencies. Grants Town is one of the original settlements established for the displaced post-emancipation. A marginalized community, it has historically suffered the socioeconomic effects of tropicalization — evidence of which is depicted in these photographs. Graffiti marked buildings bear witness to turf wars and memorials, while residents like Ms. Bernice will not cross the fence to hold conversation for fear of robbery. Despite its marginalization, Grants Town still embodies one of the strongest characteristics of Bahamian society: community.
      - Emancipation morning (photographs), 2015; 8 prints (Box 25)
        While Emancipation Day is recognized as a national holiday throughout The Bahamas, it is not celebrated anywhere else in the country as it is in Fox Hill Village. Year after year the Junkanoo community convenes on the eve of the first Monday in August to "rush" in Emancipation Day in observation of the anniversary of the abolition of slavery in the former British colony. Junkanoo is a tradition brought to these islands, from Africa, in the 17th century by means of the Atlantic Slave Trade. It is significant to note that Fox Hill Village was one of the first established land settlements granted to the newly liberated Africans post emancipation. Even more significant still, while other Junkanoo parades—during which participating groups are fully-outfitted in costumes of crepe paper and plumes— are much larger and monetized (albeit modestly), this parade is less a spectacle, more a labor of commitment to the Africans who settled this land. Junkanoo is perhaps, the largest cultural identifier for Bahamians, but despite its intrinsic value, it is largely undervalued by the community and the government. While Junkanoo has been the primary source of festival culture in The Bahamas, its lack of profitability is threatening its continued viability. The communities represented in these images celebrate this monumental, historic moment by honoring our ancestors through song and dance from 2am to sunrise despite the rainy weather conditions.
      - Human coral hybrids, 2016; 4 items (Box 17)
        This collection of 3D-printed sculptural work embodies the parity between the Africans displaced to the Bahama Islands via the Atlantic Slave Trade and the ocean. Both suffered a substantial "taming" in the name of slavery, and again at the dawn of the plantation's offspring: tourism.
      - When the lionfish came, 2016; One Apple QuickTime video file; approximately 8.9 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - O'Brien, Michaela, 2016
      O'Brien's abstract on her multi-media thesis project on Love Valley, N.C.:
      "Love Valley is currently listed on 'Visit North Carolina's' tourism website under the 'quirky' section of 'Things To Do.' Nestled in the foothills of the Brushy Mountains, the township, founded in 1954, allows only horse and foot traffic on its Main Street, a dirt road lined with less than a dozen buildings of rough hewn timber made to look a century old. This scene, that brings to mind a John Wayne movie, also conjures an eerie ghostliness at quieter times of day."
      "Founder Andy Barker's boyhood dream of a cowboy haven is home to a population which hovers at about 100 people. Ellenora, his widow, preserves a record of his utopian aspirations in a rarely accessed, dusty, woodplanked room where cabinets are filled with reels of film, medium and large format photographic negatives and piles of scrapbooks."
      "In this .2 square mile community, reenactment forms an important aspect of social life even as nostalgia contends with everyday realities. Residents attempt to shape and reshape the township around their founder's vision of a Western town full of 'good, clean fun.' In Love Valley, men, women, children, and animals each tussle for a place somewhere between an idealized past and an elusive future."
      "My time living on Main Street resulted in this fragmented narrative of frontier freedom. This assemblage is an oblique museum, an impulse to document, and a document of that impulse. In Love Valley, the complete story is eschewed for the remains: a constellation of biblical and patriotic gestures, and what lies at the heart of it all, the desire to start over."
      Most of the historical images used in the thesis were taken by Fred "Pop" Harris. Originally from Florida,he moved to Love Valley with his wife after he heard of it from those in the horse-show community. He became known as the town photographer. In his old age, he gave as a gift the negatives related to Love Valley to the founding family of Love Valley, the Barkers. He moved away from the valley in his very old age and passed away out-of-state. The negatives were cared for and stored by Ellenora Barker.
      Onsite viewing of photographic work is open without restrictions. All requests for other use, including any form of reproduction, exhibition, or within publications and other works, require the prior written permission of the donor until 2026.
      - Hand sewn gallery guide with screen printed craft paper cover (15 pages double-sided), 2016 (Box 15)
      - Plain paper printed version of photographed written thesis object (50 pages double-sided), 2016 (Box 15)
      - 10 screen prints on acid-free cotton fiber paper; 1 on vintage wallpaper, 2016; 11 prints (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Snake killer (screenprint on metal), 2016, 2 items 1 folder 2 metal strips 30 x 4 3/4 inches; and 30 3/4 x 5 1/2 inches (Oversize-folder 2)
        Handling Alert
        Metal edges of the two strips are sharp - handle with caution!
      - God's testing (screenprint on metal), approximately 17.5 x 17.5 inches square (Box 25)
      - Installation photographs, 2016; 34 TIFF image files; approximately 6.3 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - Love Valley town photographs, 2016; 24 TIFF image files; approximately 1.6 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - Miscellaneous images, 2016; One PDF and two TIFF image files; approximately 0.1 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - "Covered Dish Lunch," 2016, One MPEG-4 video file; approximately 4.0 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - "Hello Darlin," 2016, Four Apple QuickTime video files; approximately 24.1 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - "Service II," 2016, One MPEG-4 video file; approximately 3.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0010)
      - Love Valley photographs, color, contemporary, 2016, Color inkjet prints measure approximately 11 7/8 x 16 3/8 inches to 12 1/4 x 17 1/8 inches, and are printed on Hahnemuhle Fine Art Baryta paper.
        Subgroup contains fourteen color digital prints in varying sizes, created by Michaela O'Brien as part of her 2016 MFA thesis. For this project, O'Brien examines the tiny western North Carolina settlement of Love Valley, established by Andy Barker in 1954, through contemporary and archival photographs, and collages of still images, texts, and objects. The archival images and collages, in a separate subgroup, are derived from negatives and one contact sheet printed by "Pop" Harris," an inhabitant of Love Valley and its town photographer, in 1954 and 1956.
        The prints were exhibited as part of "Love Valley," an experimental documentary installation held at Cassilhaus Gallery in Chapel Hill, NC in April 2016 as part of O'Brien's MFA|EDA thesis exhibition.
        From the artist's description of the "Love Valley" project: "Built upon its deceased founder's boyhood dream of a cowboy haven, current residents must shape and reshape the township to keep their founder's utopian aspiration alive...My time living on Main Street resulted in this fragmented narrative of frontier freedom. This assemblage is an oblique museum, an impulse to document, and a document of that impulse. In Love Valley, the complete story is eschewed for the remains: a constellation of biblical and patriotic gestures, and what lies at the heart of it all, the desire to start over."
        - Ride with Bud (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Johnny Schumaker (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Payne in the afternoon (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Fountain (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Entrance (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Six shooter (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Hot tub (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Blue couch (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Wanda (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - Dale's barn (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - The chicken coop (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Black snake with baby bird (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Watermelon blue (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Town Council (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Love Valley photographs, black-and-white, historical, 2016
        These six black-and-white archival images form part of the Love Valley project, and are derived from negatives and one contact sheet printed by "Pop" Harris," a long-time inhabitant of Love Valley and its town photographer, in 1954 and 1956. Unless otherwise noted, the prints measure 11 x 14 inches. A set of color prints are in a separately described subgroub.
        - The roast (negative by Pop Harris, 1956, printed by Michaela O'Brien in 2016) (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - Calf wrangle (negative by Pop Harris, 1954, printed by Michaela O'Brien in 2016) (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - Town model (negative by Pop Harris, 1954, printed by Michaela O'Brien in 2016) (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - Moravian Falls (contact sheet by Pop Harris, 1957, printed by Michaela O'Brien, in 2016), 24 x 16 5/8 inches (Box 22, Folder 1)
          Contact sheet, enlarged, with eleven images of horses and riders enjoying the waters at the falls.
        - Andy and Ellenora, Founder's kiss (negative by Pop Harris, 1956, printed by Michaela O'Brien in 2016), 24 x 21 1/8 inchdes (Box 22, Folder 1)
        - Square circle (negative by Pop Harris, 1954, printed by Michaela O'Brien in 2016), 19 1/8 x 24 inches (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Love Valley photographs, collages, 2016
        - Necktie, Two black-and-white prints: 24 x 20 inches; 24 x 21 1/8 inches (Box 22, Folder 2)
        - Hula hoop affair, 24 x 21 1/8 inches (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Oppliger, Jason, 2016
      This collection, entitled "The Free White Sea," includes one digital file of the 30:19 film with the same name.
      Oppliger's abstract: "When you're lost in the rain in Juarez and it's Easter time too. And also of course: meat and the machine are the muscles of life. Ordinary eternal machinery. Like the grinding of stars. For even if we have the sensation of being always surrounded by our own soul, it is not as though by a motionless prison: rather, we are in some sense borne along with it in a perpetual leap to go beyond it, to reach the outside, with a sort of discouragement as we hear around us always that same resonance, which is not an echo from outside but the resounding of an internal vibration. We try to rediscover in things, now precious because of it, the glimmer that our soul projected onto them. Habit, after all, is a form of congealed remembering. An object. Like the free white sea."
      - The free white sea, 2016; One Apple QuickTime video file; approximately 19.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0009)
    - Smith, Dan, 2015-2016
      A Mess of Feesh. Smith's abstract: "Since before there was a North Carolina, generations have lived off the waters of the Core Sound. Their way of life, their love of the water, their determination to survive, their culture, language and cuisine has fed the spirit and body of the state from one generation to the next. Now, awash in globalized seafood, amidst shifting political and economic landscapes, fishermen with one foot in the past are charting a new course for their future, steeped in tradition while looking far ahead, certain that they will make it Big.
      For more than 15 months, MFAEDA Masters Candidate Dan Smith has followed the story of Eddie Willis, his wife Alison, their three year old daughter, Maggie and the dozens of family, friends and employees who work with them. Eddie, a fourth generation Harkers Island fisherman and Alison, currently appointed to the North Carolina Marine Fisheries Commission, are leading the effort to change the business model of how fishermen in North Carolina process and sell their catch, employing traditional fishing methods that have been passed down for generations amongst fishermen along the Core Sound. During this time, they have been embroiled in an ongoing political battle between the recreational and commercial fishing industries over the size of and science behind North Carolina's population of Southern Flounder. All the while, Maggie makes a playground of her parents' fish market and community sponsored fishery, which her father already envisions her inheriting, as soon as she is old enough to run a boat of her own.
      For more information and recent updates, visit: http://heydansmith.com/feesh"
      - 17 color photographs printed on Canson Palatine Fiber Rag, 13 x19 inches; include digital files, 2015-2016; 17 prints; 17 TIFF image files, approximately 2.6 gigabytes. (Box 16, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0011)
      - Gallery guide, 2016; One PDF file; approximately 0.4 megabytes. (Box 15, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0011)
      - "Weldon Willis" crab pot tag: plastic crab pot identification tag used by Eddie Willis' father, orange, 1x4 inches (Box 15)
      - Net sewing needle: plastic, 1x6 inches, green net twine (Box 15)
      - Look offshore, 2016; One MPEG-4 and one Apple QuickTime video file; approximately 39.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0011)
      - Exhibition documentation photographs, 2016; 9 TIFF image files; approximately 0.9 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0011)
    - Thomas, Christopher, 2016
      This collection comprises two digital films. One is the 30-minute thesis film, иномеханик [Images Into Arms], in .mov file format, installed in three parts in the exhibition. One is a six-minute digital movie file that documents the installation of the exhibit at the Power Plant Gallery in Durham, North Carolina from April 12-24th, 2016.
      Thomas's abstract: "An attempt to visualize forces of technological progress and their effect on the political economy of images and information. киномеханик is rhizomatic exploration of the state of visual culture from the perspective of a laid-off movie projectionist. Influenced by Dada, Russian Constructivism, and Situationist theory, the experimental multimedia installation is shaped to simulate the 21st-century parallel acceleration of evolutionary progress and spectacle as well as the obsolescence of analog technologies and visual literacy."
      - иномеханик [Images Into Arms], 2016; One Apple QuickTime video file; approximately 3.5 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0012)
      - Thesis film, 2016; One Apple QuickTime video file; approximately 20.3 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0012)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2017
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2017. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  - Written Theses, 2017
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2017 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Al-Ismaili, Salima, 2017 (Box 15)
      Shadows of Devotion
      From the artist's statement: "Shadows of Devotion is the umbrella by which three independent art projects exist as a story on feminine spirituality from different points of view." The thesis includes images from her art installation and photographs, which explore women Muslims in China and their religious culture.
    - De Francesco, Andrea, 2017 (Box 15)
      Kurdish Stories
      Companion piece to wax, ink, and paper collage art installation, and film on Kurdish refugees and society. From the artist's statement: "My work is a dialogue between so-called high culture and formal poetics and the popular culture of a selected group such as the Kurdish refugees." The written thesis includes color images of the artwork and stills from the video.
    - Borst, Sarah Elizabeth, 2017 (Box 15)
      This is Mine
      Companion piece to the filmed performance art, art installation, and photographs. From the artist's statement: "This is Mine is a four-part project that confronts the sexualization of the female form and the proliferation of the feminine ideal." The written thesis contains many color reproductions of photographs and diary pages.
    - Herbold, Sylvia, 2017 (Box 15)
      A Path Seems Like a Place
      In the written theses, the author discusses other multimedia performance and films dealing with women's sexualities and bodies, and compares them with her own work.
      From the artist's statement: "This film is a way of theorizing how women reclaim everyday spaces, improvise through performance, and find female autonomy."
    - Mueller, Lauren, 2017 (Box 15)
      Huro Huro
      A companion piece to her film on conservation centers for gibbons in the U.S., India, and Thailand. "Huro huro" is the name for this primate in the Indian language Garo.
    - Pesci, Colleen F., 2017 (Box 15)
      dear; companion
      A companion piece to her film, which explores the relationships between twins, particularly the process of grieving when one twin experiences the loss of the other, and by extension, any great loss and its meaning to a person's future identity.
    - Shafer, Anthony Dean, 2017 (Box 15)
      Binary
      Companion thesis to the performance, film, and installation. The written thesis includes images of the installation and the performance piece, as well as archival and family photographs, photographs of a historical figure, Mary Wood, and excerpts from her diaries.
      From the artist's statement: "By entwining the stories of Mary Blood and myself and expanding the cinematic possibility into an interactive installation made in part of objects sculpted with direction from the divined spirit of madness, taming it enough to give it shape from unknowable form, I hope to show how art can repurpose trauma and turn it into something else: an entirely different memory and history and into the conjoined sensations made transferable to audiences."
    - Stephens, Kate, 2017 (Box 15)
      Fret Not
      From the artist's statement: "My written thesis...is an annotated script of my final thesis performance. The script is in bold...My thesis focuses on the last weeks of my godmother Sue Henry's life and her ongoing role in my life, particularly as a spiritual guide during a time of crisis in the year following her death." The memoir includes color images from the performance film.
    - Sudak, Jason, 2017 (Box 15)
      Great Dismal Swamp
      From the artist's statement: "The passages that follow are a tangle of fugitive texts, representing a web of social, historical, and aesthetic approaches to documenting and inhabiting the Great Dismal Swamp and ohter contested landscapes. In conjunction with the film, they aim not to memorialize, criticize, or contextualize the past, but to transform the materials of the past into resources for the future; to reclaim territories that have been hiding in plain sight."
    - Xin, Ran, 2017 (Box 15)
      Missing Persons